Montgomery Sicard Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Montgomery Sicard Papers 1800-1948 (bulk 1870-1898)
MSS53207
Sicard, Montgomery, 1836-1900
1,200 items
4 containers
2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer. Correspondence, subject file, and miscellaneous material relating to Sicard’s naval career, including diagrams and memoranda for breech-loading howitzers and his plans for steel armor plate for ships.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Chandler, William E. (William Eaton), 1835-1917--Correspondence.; Floyd, William, fl. 1800-1839--Correspondence.; Folger, William Mayhew, 1844-1928--Correspondence.; Hunt, William H. (William Henry), 1823-1884--Correspondence.; O'Neil, Charles, 1842-1927--Correspondence.; Porter, David D. (David Dixon), 1813-1891--Correspondence.; Sicard, Eleanor L.--Correspondence.; Sicard, Elizabeth Floyd, 1835- --Correspondence.; Sicard, George J.--Correspondence.; Sicard, Montgomery, 1836-1900.; Sicard, Montgomery, Jr.--Correspondence.; Sicard, Stephen, Jr.--Correspondence.; Sicard, Stephen, Sr. Stephen Sicard, Sr., papers.; Sicard, William F.--Correspondence.; Walker, Asa, 1845-1916--Correspondence.
Subjects
Armor-plate.; Artillery.; Howitzers.; Naval architecture.; Shipbuilding.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of Montgomery Sicard, naval officer, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1964 and converted to a gift in 1998.
Additional Guides
In 1979 the Library published Nathan Sargent, John Shaw, Montgomery Sicard, and Roger Welles: Registers of Their Papers in the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Montgomery Sicard are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1836, Sept. 30 Born, New York, N.Y.
1855 Graduated, U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md. Duty in USS Potomac, Home Squadron
1856 Duty in USS Wabash, Home Squadron
1860 Duty in USS Dacotah, East India Squadron
1862 1863 Duty in USS Oneida, West Gulf Blockading Squadron
1863 Married Elizabeth Floyd
1864 Duty in USS Ticonderoga, South Atlantic Blockading Squadron
1865 Commanded USS Seneca; in charge of the left wing of the 2nd Naval Division
1869 Commanded USS Saginaw, Pacific Fleet
1871. Ordnance duty, U.S. Navy Yard, New York, N.Y
1872 Ordnance duty, U.S. Navy Yard, Washington, D.C.
1877 Duty in designing and constructing the first steel breech-loading guns for the U.S. Navy
1881 Promoted to captain
1881 1897 Chief, Bureau of Ordnance
1891 1893 Commanded USS Miantonomoh
1897 Promoted to rear admiral Commander in chief, Naval Forces, North Atlantic Station
1898 President, Strategy Board, during the Spanish-American War Retired from the U.S. Navy
1900, Sept. 14 Died, Westernville, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Montgomery Sicard (1836-1900) span the years 1800-1948, with the bulk of the material falling in the years 1870 to 1898. The collection consists of official and general correspondence, a subject file, and miscellaneous items.
Sicard’s achievements in the field of ordnance are documented with his diagrams and memoranda for breech-loading howitzers and his plans for steel armor plate for ships. In his plans for steel plates are holograph and typescript notes, memoranda, letters, blueprints, and a corrected galley for Specifications for Armor for the United States Navy.
The official correspondence includes a few letters, but the majority of items are orders to duty. Correspondents include William E. Chandler, William Mayhew Folger, William H. Hunt, Charles O’Neil, and David D. Porter. The general correspondence consists largely of letters exchanged between Sicard and his wife, Elizabeth Floyd Sicard, and between the Sicards and their children, William F. Sicard, Montgomery Sicard, Jr., and Eleanor L. Sicard. Other correspondents are Ward Hunt, Jr., Kossuth Niles, and Asa Walker.
Sicard’s financial affairs are documented with letters of advice on investments; papers of profits, management of property, and purchase of household goods, and tax receipts. There are letters from his brothers, Stephen Sicard and George J. Sicard, and his brother-in-law, William Floyd.
Of interest in the miscellany are trade papers of Sicard’s father, Stephen Sicard, and papers on the management of the Floyds’ property in New York.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is organized by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Official, 1868-1889, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - General (Box 1)
    - 1864-1885, (9 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1886-1900, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Letters of condolence, 1900-1901, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Subject file (Box 2)
  - Breech-loading howitzers, undated (Box 2)
  - Financial papers (Box 2)
    - 1862-1879, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1800-1900, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Spanish-American War, 1898 (Box 3)
  - Steel armor plate, 1895, undated (Box 3)
    - Blueprints (Box 3)
    - Contracts (Box 3)
    - Notes and memoranda, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Wreck of the USS Saginaw on Ocean Island (1870), 1871-1948 (Box 3)
- Miscellany (Box 4)
  - Biographical file, undated (Box 4)
  - Card plates, 1900 (Box 4)
  - Certificate, Associated Veterans of Farragut’s Fleet, undated (Box 4)
  - Genealogy (Box 4)
  - Holograph compositions, 1851, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous material (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1899-1900, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Notebook, fund for the relief of the families of John Andrews and James Muir, 1871-1877 (Box 4)
  - Photograph of Sicard, undated (Box 4)
  - Printed matter, 1847-1889 (Box 4)
  - Signatures Sketches, USS Swatara, 1878 (Box 4)
  - Stephen Sicard, financial papers, 1821-1825 (Box 4)
  - William F. Sicard, notebook and essay, 1887-1888 (Box 4)
  - William Floyd, financial papers, 1800-1839 (Box 4)